# **Tengxiang Zhang**

I am an Associate Research Scientist at the Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. My research interests include: 1) Novel sensing and interaction techniques; 2) Tag-aided wireless spatial computing; 3) Semantic-based interaction abstraction theory and application.

# **EDUCATION**

2016-2019	PhD, Human Computer Interaction, Computer Science	
	Tsinghua University, China	Advisor: Prof. Yuanchun Shi
2011-2013	MSc, Electromagnetics, Electrical Engineering	
	The University of Texas at Austin, USA	Advisor: Prof. Andrea Alu
2007-2011	BSc, Chien-Shiung Wu Honors College/Electrical Engineering	
	Southeast University, China	Research supervisor: Prof. Tiejun Cui

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- 2022 [C.4] Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen, Benfeng Xu, and **Tengxiang Zhang**\*. 2022. ModalDrop: Modality-aware Regularization for Temporal-Spectral Fusion in Human Activity Recognition. ICASSP'23 (submitted).
  - [J.8] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zitong Lan, Chenren Xu, Yanrong Li, and Yiqiang Chen. 2022. BLEselect: Gestural IoT Device Selection via Bluetooth Angle of Arrival Estimation from Smart Glasses. 2022. IMWUT. 6, 4. (accepted)
  - [O.6] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Xin Jiang, Xuhai Xu, Anind K Dey, and Yiqiang Chen. 2022. BoldMove: Enabling IoT Device Control on Ubiquitous Touch Interfaces by Semantic Mapping and Sequential Selection. In Extended Abstracts of the CHI 2022, 7.
  - [J.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zi Qian, HsuanWei Fan, Jie Ren, Yuntao Wang, Yuanchun Shi. Easily-add Battery-free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects: A System Implementation and Usability Study. *CCF Transactions on Pervasive Computing and Interaction*.
  - 2021 [O.5] Xin Zeng,Xinyi Yang,**Tengxiang Zhang**,Yukang Yan,Yiqiang Chen. ScreenJump: An AR-facilitated User-centric Interaction System for Fine-grained Resource Manipulation Across Displays. *CHI 2021 Workshop on User Experience for Multi-Device Ecosystems: Challenges and Opportunities*.
    - [J.6] Yingwei Zhang, Yiqiang Chen, Hanchao Yu, Zeping Lv, Xiaodong Yang, Chunyu Hu, **Tengxiang Zhang**. What Can "Drag & Drop" Tell? Detecting Mild Cognitive Impairment by Hand Motor Function Assessment under Dual-Task Paradigm. *International Journal of Human-Computer Studies* 145:102547.
  - **2020** [C.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Ke Sun, Yuntao Wang, and Yiqiang Chen. 2020. ThermalRing: Gesture and Tag Inputs Enabled by a Thermal Imaging Smart Ring. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20), 1–13.
    - [C.2] Yuntao Wang, Zichao (Tyson) Chen, Hanchuan Li, Zhengyi Cao, Huiyi Luo, Tengxiang Zhang, Ke Ou, John Raiti, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. 2020. MoveVR: Enabling Multiform Force Feedback in Virtual Reality

- using Household Cleaning Robot. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20), 1–12.
- [O.4] **Tengxiang Zhang** and Steve Hodges. New Opportunities for Sustainable Interaction using Backscatter Sensors. *Workshop on self-powered sustainable interfaces and interactions (SelfSustainableCHI 2020)*
- **2019** [J.5] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Jiayuan Gao, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Simin Li, Yuanchun Shi. Facilitating Temporal Synchronous Target Selection through User Behavior Modeling. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 2,4:159.
  - [J.4] Yuntao Wang, Jianyu Zhou, Hanchuan Li, Tengxiang Zhang, Minxuan Gao, Zhuolin Cheng, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. FlexTouch: Enabling Large-Scale Interaction Sensing Beyond Touchscreens Using Flexible and Conductive Materials. Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol., 3,3:109.
  - [O.3] Jianfei Shen, **Tengxiang Zhang**, and Yiqiang Chen. Tap2Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Tapping. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '19*, *Pages 346-349*.
- **2018** [J.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Yiqin Lu, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. Tap-to-Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Synchronous Tapping. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 2, 4: 201.
  - [O.2] **Tengxiang Zhang.** 2018. Toward Pervasive Interaction: Empowering and Enriching Interactions on Resource-constrained Devices. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '18*, Pages 504-509.
  - [O.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. TOUCHPOWER: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *GetMobile: Mobile Comp. and Comm.* 22, 2: 27–31. (Invited Highlights)
- **2017** [J.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. TouchPower: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 1, 3: 121:1–121:20. (*Discussion Paper*)
  - [C.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Nicholas Becker, Yuntao Wang, Yuan Zhou, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. BitID: Easily Add Battery-Free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects. *In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing (SMARTCOMP)*, 1–8. (Best Paper Runner-up)
- 2013 [J.1] Huifeng Ma, Bengeng Cai, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yan Yang, Weixiang Jiang, and Tiejun Cui. 2013. Three-Dimensional Gradient-Index Materials and Their Applications in Microwave Lens Antennas. *IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation* 61, 5: 2561–2569.

<sup>\*</sup> Corresponding author

## **PATENTS**

- **2022** [P.11] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yanrong Li, Yiqiang Chen. Smart Glasses-based Facial Action Unit Detection Method and Apparatus *(pending)* 
  - [P.10] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Zitong Lan, Yanrong Li, Yiqiang Chen. A Device Selection System and Method: CN 202211410562.4 *(pending)*
  - [P.9] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. An AR Device Felicitated Multi-Device Interaction System and Method: CN 202211490160.X *(pending)*
- **2021** [P.8] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Semantic-based Device Association Method: CN 202110359565.9 *(pending)*
- **2020** [P.7] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Gesture Recognition Method and System: CN 202010411317.X
  - [P.6] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. Apparatus and Method for Cognitive Load Analysis Based on Near-infrared Imaging of Subcutaneous Veins: CN 202010459503.0
  - [P.5] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method and System: CN 202010425034.0
- **2018** [P.4] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. One type of Smart Ring: CN 201821371671.9
  - [P.3] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, Tengxiang Zhang. Smart Ring: CN 201821371641.8
  - [P.2] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang and Chun Yu. Pairing method and wireless device for pairing using wireless signals. International Patent No. PCT/CN2018/094468.
  - [P.1] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu. An association method and apparatus to pair devices based on wireless signals: CN 201810723952.4

## **GRANTS**

- **2022** [I.5] **Principle Investigator:** Research on Pervasive Touch Interface and Interaction Design for IoT Device Control (300K CNY). NSFC Fund for Young Scholars.
- **2021** [I.4] **Principle Investigator:** Ultra-low-power Bluetooth-compatible Ubiquitous Touch Interface (20K CNY). Open project, Beijing Key Laboratory of Mobile Computing and Pervasive Device.
- **2020** [I.3] **Principle Executing Investigator:** A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method (650K CNY). ICT, CAS Innovation Fund.
  - [I.2] Co-Principle Investigator: Resources Cross-modality Association and Matching Techniques (2.28 Million CNY), sub-project of Key Technologies for Modern Service Resource Management, National Key Research and Development Plan.
  - [I.1] **Co-investigator:** Hearing Aid Automatic Fitting Models (270K CNY), Key Technologies of Proactive Health and Aging Population, National Key Research and Development Plan.

## **HONORS AND AWARDS**

2019 Graduate with Honor (CS), Tsinghua University, China

2018 Finalist, Global Innovation Competition'182017 Best Paper Runner-up, SMARTCOMP'17

2017 Discussion Paper, UbiComp'17

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2021- Associate Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology,

Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

2019-2021 Assistant Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology,

Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

 Conduct research on pervasive sensing and interactive systems and pervasive interaction techniques

Published papers on top-tier journals and conferences like CHI and IMWUT

• Granted research funds ~3 million CNY with 2 National Key Research and Development Plan funds

2015-2016 RF Engineer/Product Manager, Tomoon Technology, Beijing, China

Smartwatch and Bluetooth tracker antenna design

• Bluetooth tracker product definition, project management, field deployment

2013-2015 Product and Test Engineer, Silicon Labs, Austin, Texas, USA

• IoT MCU chips (e.g. Sub-GHz, ZigBee) RF calibration and test

• Test program (C/Perl) development, hardware design and layout

• Developed on-chip test program that saved over 30% test time for EM357

#### **SERVICES**

**Committee Member** SIGCHI Sustainability Committee

CCF HCI Technical Program Committee CCF Ubicomp Technical Program Committee

**Review** CHI'20'21'22, IMWUT'21'22, UIST'20, MobileHCI'20, ISS'20,

IUI'20, TEI'20, EICS'19, TEI'21 WIP Program Committee

**Volunteer** ACM UBICOMP/ISWC 2018, Singapore;

The 4th UN World Urban Forum 2008, Nanjing, China

Academic Speaker Microsoft Research (Redmond)

GIX ACSP (Access Computing Summer Program) 2020

**Mentor** GIX ACSP '21'22, GIX 2019 Winter Camp

Chair HHME (largest conference for HCI and ubicomp in China) 2022 Tutorial

# STUDENT SUPERVISION AND MENTORSHIP

Xin ZengUCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang ChenJiayuan GaoUCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang ChenYanrong LiUCAS Master (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen

Xiaoyu Wang Peking University Undergraduate (CS)
Zhengtai Gou Tsinghua Undergraduate (Automation)

\*Zitong Lan SEU Undergraduate (CS)
\*Xinran Chen UESTC Undergraduate (CS)

\*Yaobin Su University of Copenhagen Master (CS)

\*Xinyi Yang BJTU Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at CUHK

\*Jiayin Wang

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Tsinghua (CS)

\*Simin Li

Beihang Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Georgia Tech (CS)

\*Zi Qian

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at U of Toronto (CS)

\*Hsuan-Wei Fan

Tsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Cornell Tech (CS)

\*Hanwei Wang

Tsinghua Undergraduate (Physics); Now Ph.D at UIUC (EE)

\* Alumni

# **SKILLS**

**Programming languages:** Python, C, C++, C#, Java, Matlab

**Prototyping**: Arduino, Processing, Altium, 3D printing

**Software:** Matlab, CST, Keras, Scikit-learn

**Hardware**: Signal generator, Vector network analyzer, Spectrum analyzer

# **REFEREES**

Yuanchun Shi, Professor, Tsinghua University, Ph.D supervisor.

Email: ycshi@tsinghua.edu.cn

Steve Hodges, Senior Principal Researcher, Microsoft Research Cambridge, Collaborator

Email: steve.hodges@microsoft.com

Chenren Xu, Associate Professor, Peking University, Collaborator

Email: chenren@pku.edu.cn